<section1
	topic='Buddycloud Introduction'
	anchor='Buddycloud Introduction'>
	<section2
		topic='About Buddycloud'
		anchor='about-buddycloud'>
		<p>Buddycloud is a collection of services, running as XMPP components
			that enable rich, federated communications between individuals and
			groups. Buddycloud builds on XMPP's native federation and pub-sub
			principles to connect to and synchronise content with followers on
			local and remote Buddycloud servers.
		</p>
	</section2>
	<section2
		topic='Buddycloud Channels'
		anchor='Buddycloud Channels'>
		<p>
			Buddycloud channels are a bundle of pub-sub nodes presented as a
			JID-like name (example:
			<link url='buddycloud:juliet@capulit.lit'>juliet@capulet.lit</link>
			. Content posted into channels is automatically synchronised to the
			correct followers on other Buddycloud servers.
		</p>
	</section2>
	<section2
		topic='Glossary'
		anchor='glossary'>
		<dl>
			<di>
				<dt>Personal Channel</dt>
				<dd> Personal channels are a group of pub-sub nodes that have the
					same owner, followers and access permissions.
				</dd>
			</di>
			<di>
				<dt>Topic Channel</dt>
				<dd>Topic channels are for group discussions and decoupled from the
					owners jid. For example balcony-speeches@topics.montague.lit could
					be owned by speechwriter@montague.lit.
				</dd>
			</di>
			<di>
				<dt>Ephemeral Channel</dt>
				<dd>
					Ephemeral channels, are generated for one-off use and automatically
					removed by the Buddycloud server after the last participant
					unfollows them (similar to the Google Hangout service) An example
					ephemeral channel would be
					<code>125bd2c4-afc2-4d4c-b869-efc0c0dad8c5@montague.lit</code>
					.
				</dd>
			</di>
			<di>
				<dt>Buddycloud Server</dt>
				<dd>An XMPP component which hosts channel nodes and provides an
					interface conforming to this document to allow access to them via
					XMPP.
				</dd>
			</di>
			<di>
				<dt>Home Server</dt>
				<dd>The Buddycloud server responsible for a JID's channels and Inbox.
				</dd>
			</di>
			<di>
				<dt>Remote Server</dt>
				<dd>Buddycloud servers that run on other XMPP domains.
				</dd>
			</di>
			<di>
				<dt>Buddycloud Inbox</dt>
				<dd>Service on the Entity's Home Server which subscribes to nodes on
					the Entity's behalf, and may cache node data and provide an ability
					to replay recent messages.
				</dd>
			</di>
		</dl>
	</section2>
</section1>
