<section1 topic='Buddycloud Introduction' anchor='intro'>
	<section2 topic='About Buddycloud' anchor='about-buddycloud'>
		<p>Buddycloud is a collection of services, running as XMPP components
			that enable rich, federated communications between individuals and
			groups. Buddycloud builds on XMPP's native federation and pub-sub
			principles to connect to and synchronise content with followers on
			local and remote Buddycloud servers.
		</p>
	</section2>
	<section2 topic='About Channels' anchor='channels-intro'>
		<p>
			Buddycloud channels are a bundle of pub-sub nodes presented as a
			JID-like name (for example, buddycloud:juliet@capulet.lit). There are
			two types of channel:
			<ul>
				<li>user channels (named after the user's JID), for example
					romeo@montague.lit) and,
				</li>
				<li>topic channels, for example
					balcony-speeches@topics.montague.lit) which are owned by the
					channel creator and (usually) named after the content.
				</li>
			</ul>
			Content posted into channels is automatically synchronised to the
			correct followers on other Buddycloud servers.
		</p>
	</section2>
	<section2 topic='Glossary' anchor='glossary'>
		<dl>
			<di>
				<dt>Personal Channel</dt>
				<dd> Personal channels are a group of pub-sub nodes that have the
					same owner, folllowers and access permissions.
				</dd>
			</di>
			<di>
				<dt>Topic Channel</dt>
				<dd> Topic channels are decoupled from the owners jid. For example
					balcony-speeches@topics.montague.lit could be owned by a jid,
					speechwriter@montague.lit. Topic channels have different default
					settings and default nodes.
				</dd>
			</di>
			<di>
				<dt>Budycloud Server</dt>
				<dd>An XMPP component which hosts channel nodes and provides an
					interface conforming to this document to allow access to them via
					XMPP.
				</dd>
			</di>
			<di>
				<dt>Home Server</dt>
				<dd>The Buddycloud server that maintains a user's channels and
					Inbox.
				</dd>
			</di>
			<di>
				<dt>Remote Server</dt>
				<dd>Buddycloud servers that run on other XMPP domains.
				</dd>
			</di>
			<di>
				<dt>Buddycloud Inbox</dt>
				<dd> Service on the Entity's Home Server which subscribes to nodes
					on the Entity's behalf, and may cache node data and provide an
					ability to replay recent messages.
				</dd>
			</di>
		</dl>
	</section2>
</section1>