<section1 topic='Buddycloud Introduction' anchor='Buddycloud Introduction'>
	<section2 topic='About Buddycloud' anchor='about-buddycloud'>
		<p>The Buddycloud project is a set of independently deployable services, that
			inter-operate to create a rich collaboration service.
		</p>
		<p>Buddycloud Channels build on XMPP's native federation and publish-subscribe
			principles to connect to, and synchronise content with users on local and
			remote domains. Services are designed to interoperate. For example, the Media
			Server, Friend Finder, and content recommendation engine work together to help
			developers build a unified collaboration services for individual and groups
			of users.
		</p>
		<p>This XEP seeks to define how the Buddycloud Channel service currently
			functions. It also seeks stay extensible for accommodate future, undefined
			use cases.
		</p>
	</section2>
	<section2 topic='Buddycloud Channels' anchor='Buddycloud Channels'>
		<p>
			Buddycloud channels are a bundle of <cite>XEP-0060</cite> publish-subscribe nodes with 
			identical subscribers and permissions presented as a JID-like
			name (example:
			<link url='buddycloud:juliet@capulit.lit'>juliet@capulet.lit</link>
			. Content posted into channels is automatically synchronised to the correct
			followers on other Buddycloud domains.
		</p>
	</section2>
	<section2 topic='Glossary' anchor='glossary'>
		<dl>
			<di>
				<dt>Personal Channel</dt>
				<dd> Personal channels are a group of pub-sub nodes that have the same
					owner, followers and access permissions.
				</dd>
			</di>
			<di>
				<dt>Topic Channel</dt>
				<dd>Topic channels are for group discussions and decoupled from the owners
					jid. For example balcony-speeches@topics.montague.lit could be owned by
					speechwriter@montague.lit.
				</dd>
			</di>
			<di>
				<dt>Ephemeral Channel</dt>
				<dd>
					Ephemeral channels, are generated for one-off use and automatically removed
					by the Buddycloud service after the last participant unfollows them
					(similar to the Google Hangout service) An example ephemeral channel would
					be
					<code>125bd2c4-afc2-4d4c-b869-efc0c0dad8c5@montague.lit</code>
					.
				</dd>
			</di>
			<di>
				<dt>Buddycloud Service</dt>
				<dd>An XMPP component which hosts channel nodes and provides an interface
					conforming to this document to allow access to them via XMPP.
				</dd>
			</di>
			<di>
				<dt>Home server</dt>
				<dd>The Buddycloud service responsible for a JID's channels and Inbox.
				</dd>
			</di>
			<di>
				<dt>Remote Server</dt>
				<dd>Buddycloud service that run on other XMPP domains.
				</dd>
			</di>
			<di>
				<dt>Buddycloud Inbox</dt>
				<dd>Service on the entity's home Buddycloud service which subscribes to
					nodes on the Entity's behalf, and may cache node data and provide an
					ability to replay recent messages.
				</dd>
			</di>
		</dl>
	</section2>
</section1>
